Katharine Jeanette Bush Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
Katharine Jeanette Bush Archives
1879-1915
IZAR.000996
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
3
Archives of Katharine J. Bush related to her work and reasearch at Yale Univeristy and the Peabody Museum.
Bush, Katharine Jeannette, 1855-1937
Biographical Sketch
In 1901, Katharine Jeannette Bush (b. 1855, d. 1937) became the first woman at Yale University to receive a Ph.D. in the sciences. Nearly 46 years old at the time, she had worked as assistant to Addison E. Verrill for over 20 years. Initially hired to help arrange and catalog specimens that were accumulating as a result of Verrill?s involvement with the U.S. Fish Commission, Katharine Bush eventually collaborated with him on several important reviews of shallow and deepwater Mollusca of the Atlantic coastal region.
Bush's most significant work, which also served as her dissertation, was an important monograph on the sabellid and serpulid polychaetes collected by the Harriman Alaska Expedition of 1899, and published in 1905. Considering the Victorian era she lived in, it is not surprising that Bush was not a member of the expedition; the polychaetes she studied were collected primarily by her brother-in-law Wesley R. Coe, a faculty member at Yale. During her 30-year career, Bush published 19 research articles and monographs, an enduring scientific achievement matched by few women of her era.
Description of the Material
These archives encompass materials related to her work and research at the Peabody Museum. They include manuscript related materials, correspondence, etc.
USA; Connecticut; Alaska; Atlantic Ocean; Bermuda; Manuscript materials; Correspondence; Record books; Yale Peabody Museum; Yale University
- Manuscript Related Materials, 1879-1914; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  These are materials related to manuscripts. The contain line drawings, figures, rough drafts, etc.
  - Miscellaneous. Miscellaneous archives related to Bush manuscripts., 1879-1914; 001544
    - Miscellaneous. Lists of Mollusca, Cnidaria, etc. Some appear to deal with Bermuda specimens. Possibly used in Verrill and Bush paper on Bermuda., 1879-1914; 001545
    - Miscellaneous. Numerous, figures, notes, lists, etc. Found bound together., 1879-1914; 001561
  - Mollusca. Manuscript materials related to Mollusca., 1879-1914; 000998
    - Mollusca. These are line drawings and figures of various gastropods and bivalves, mostly from collections made by the U.S. Fish Commission. The drawings all appear done by K.J. Bush, and several have annotations from A.E. Verrill. Many also have associated USNM numbers and USFC station numbers. They may have been used in various A.E. Verrill and K.J. Bush publications. Several are of type speicmens that are in the USNM and possibly YPM collections., 1880-1900; 000999
    - Mollusca. 2 figures. One of Bela incisula and the other Bela pleurotomaria. Both used in Bush, K.J. 1883. Proc. USNM. 6: 236-247. pl.9. They are fig. 7 & 10., 1880-1900; 001570
    - Mollusca. Figures of Mollusca, such as Cylichna, Actaeon, etc., 1880-1900; 001641
    - Mollusca. 13 figures. Used in Bush, K.J. 1883. Proc. U.S.N.M. 6: 236-247, pl 9. They include Fig. 1, 1a, 2-5, 5a, 6, 9, 11-14., 001647
    - Mollusca. 13 figures. Used in Bush, K.J. 1897. Trans. Conn. Acad. Arts Sci. 10: 97-144. Includes in text Fig. 1, 2, 3a-c, 4, 5, 5a, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10., 001646
- Correspondence, 1879-1914; Series II
  Correspondence of K.J. Bush.
  - John Percy Moore Correspondence. Correspondence from J.P. Moore to K.J. Bush., 1910; 001699
    - John Percy Moore Correspondence. A letter from J.P. Moore thanking Bush for the Spirobis she had sent him., 19 Sep 1910; 001700